software engineering radio episode 74
the real enterprise architecture
[Music]
hello folks welcome to software
engineering radio this is Marcus
although the episode will be done by
Alex and Wolfgang hello I just wanted to
make two short announcements before we
get to the meat of the matter one is I
wanted to remind you that our experiment
is still running the experiment being
that we've decided to see whether the
donations we could get from you the
audience the level of donations we could
get is high enough so we don't need any
sponsoring and still can cover our cost
for website audio equipment press
releases and all the other stuff we need
so in the last couple of weeks since
we've announced this idea on the survey
results episode we have received quite a
bit of donations it's not yet at the
level where we want to be and I also
promised that I'll be completely open
about how much we've got and well I'll
let you know once the the experimental
period is over
basically meaning at the end of the year
so please if you haven't donated yet
please consider donating you will really
help us cover our cost the second thing
I wanted to mention is that we wanted to
try to make as you radio a bit more
interactive specifically we want to
include more audience participation in
the widest sense we've decided to do two
things one is we'll do a well listener
feedback episode not in the sense we've
had before that I read comments that
you've sent us know what we what we want
to do is that we pre announce the time
when we'll actually do the episode and
you'll be able to call in to the
recording via Skype and ask us questions
or give us comments or discuss certain
topics we don't yet know when this is
going to happen we have to find the time
and we'll probably do this in the
evening European time so the Europeans
can call and in the evening and us folks
can
Hollan at their during their morning and
well it's probably sometime in the night
in Asia but we can't accommodate
everybody of course and and the idea is
just to discuss things and have you
participate a bit more than what we've
done in the past we let you know details
as soon as we know when exactly this is
going to happen the other thing with
regards to interactivity is that on
January 26th I think we have the second
anniversary anniversary of se radio
coming up and we want to celebrate that
a little bit and the way we want to
celebrate that is that we will do a
special episode in which we will just
play comments basically congratulations
feedback and other stuff that you send
us so if you would like to participate
just record the SU radio birthday
message one minute one minute and 20 or
whatever mp3 file 256 kilobyte encoding
and and send it over a team at se -
radio dotnet and we'll consider it for
playing it on the birthday show okay so
much for the announcements let's now get
to this episode's content it's a
discussion about enterprise architecture
with Wolfgang Keller hosted by Alex you
will remember that we've already had an
episode about enterprise architecture at
or at least about what we called
Enterprise Architecture and it was about
the technical aspects of enterprise
architecture and we got feedback from
several people that and the project
architectures are actually something
different and it's more about a
managerial task of managing all the
architectural assets and applications
and systems in a large enterprise so
this time we really deliver on the title
and discuss this more managerial
organizational not so much technical
aspect of enterprise architecture I'm
here together with Wolfgang Keller who
is not only a very experienced in the
field and has many years of experience
and with enterprise architecture but
also has written a book on the topic
which is called IT Antony means are
hidding to him the name is also the hint
that it's just in Sherman right now so
unfortunately for you
English guys it's not available in
English as far as I know yet so maybe
what can could you introduce yourself a
bit yes okay as you already mentioned my
name is Wolfgang Keller if somebody
should hear something which sounds a
little bit strange I'm very sorry um I
got a little cold so we tried anyway
yeah what did I do I studied computer
science and Business Administration and
unique at Technical University
everybody knows Munich or many people
seem to know Munich it's famous for beer
Oktoberfest it's not so famous for
computer science but I can tell you yeah
we we've got a reasonable faculty over
there after my studies I had to learn
yeah
to do something in practice in my case
it was kind of big project business at a
company which is called software design
and management which is this German
company and they are specializing in
providing very big software systems for
our are these guys called in Fortune 500
clients and blue chip clans in Germany I
stayed with them for about seven years
was very interesting and they liked it a
lot after that I got the chance to take
responsibility for an international life
insurance platform for a company called
Ginny Ronnie Vienna group generally is
one of the world's biggest insurance
companies and as you all know insurance
and finance companies have a very large
software portfolio usually because
everything they do is information and
software and they do not manufacture any
tangible things so it's all about
software and information there um I was
there for about eight years and I did a
few things like managing the technical
side of the largest Smalltalk project in
Europe at the times later I was in
charge of enterprise architecture is
what we're gonna talk
today and also the things like a euro
conversion your conversion is very
interesting because you have to keep
track of converting all the applications
of a company that makes a turnover of
roughly let's say four five billion
euros which is not nothing and if this
goes wrong you've got a pretty problem
so yes I'm kind of like in the business
of taming the big iron and computer
science
okay now it's your hair like you already
gave some hints if someone knows what's
enterprise architecture nevertheless I
guess we have to give a short
explanation what enterprise architecture
means because there's a lot of confusion
out there as far as I know yes it is and
I sure you want I'm sure you want an
elevator talk enterprise architecture is
about managing the portfolio of
applications of large scale companies
who need to perform the business with
these applications if you are a normal
software architect you usually deal with
maybe a very big application like the
thing I mentioned the small talk
platform or project had roughly
something like fifteen thousand function
points which is a mega project but if
you compare it to the whole landscape of
such a company than this is only not
even ten percent of all the software
they have so if your normal Software
Architect you deal with one of those
projects but if you are an Enterprise
Architect you need to keep track of
let's say 200 more of those applications
if you look at a large company like BMW
which is very famous all around the
world in America for their nice cars
yeah and these guys have about 4,000
applications and they use an IT budget
of roughly but more than a billion euros
per year and
is really quite something and as the
enterprise architecture division at that
place takes care that the company gets
some money or some value for money sorry
yes this is this was the elevator talk I
have a whole lecture on this which takes
15 times 90 minutes and after that
students still thought and they could
kind of like hear more and more and more
but yeah it's it's quite an amazing feel
yeah absolutely I often hear people are
coming to talks from me when I talked
about Enterprise Act architecture and
they were surprised not to have hear
anything about software patterns and EJB
or whatever so it's it's more about yeah
managing portfolio complete IT whatever
and not so much about the software
architecture of a single system you have
to touch this as well but from a
different point of view so what exactly
would you say is the difference between
software architecture and application
architecture I guess we be yeah already
you you almost said it software
architecture deals with the architecture
of a single systems yeah maybe also with
the architecture of a family of systems
yeah for example in software
architectures as you'd mentioned already
of such terms as patterns you have
layers you have architectural views you
have different views upon a software
architect effect like let's say a
process architecture deployment
architecture listen listen that
architecture but in order to make
decisions about portfolio this is all
not very necessary because for example
what interests you if you deal with the
portfolio as what are the retirement
candidates what are the systems you need
to invest in what are the gaps in your
portfolio where your business needs some
more software and all the like
enterprise architecture is a bit of an
emerging discipline if you look at
what the researchers did and you could
see in the middle of the 19th I also
deal dealt lot was software architecture
and at that time as I did a lot at
Carnegie Mellon University and I started
to research description languages for
architecture and formal description
techniques and all this kind of stuff
and what came out was that all those
theories about viewpoints and views and
architectural views and patterns their
arcane patterns was not them but anyway
um that kind of research started about
let's say 12 15 years ago and it's got a
kind of maturity right now if you look
at the enterprise architecture it
started only three four five years ago
and it's still an evolving field and
that makes it kind of interesting you
know yeah exactly
last time I tried to explain a friend
what enterprise architecture is he first
didn't really understand what I mean and
after that he said ah you mean IT
governance is it IT governance so is it
I teach evidence is there a difference
what is IT governance because it's
closely related I would say Enterprise
Architecture is a part of our Qi
governance if you have any acid in the
company like let's say real estate or
your products portfolio or whatever it
needs some kind of governance yeah if
you look at the dictionaries and it says
that governance is the process of
governing the country and if I have to
translate it into German it's like e
Hong and in English its governance yeah
so this is kind of like a very basic
term or a very very basic thing yeah
yeah so if you have any resource you
like your IT you know which is a major
resource and most companies because they
burned something like 5% of the costs or
more sometimes more sometimes less yeah
then this needs governance you know so
and your IT usually smore
and only your application portfolio you
are teased about managing GRT or RT is
about changing processes your IT is
about managing your asses what you have
and all of this is governance and some
people would also say that governance or
IT governance deals with who decides
what in RT of a company you know and
this is not exactly what Enterprise
Architecture is kind of like enterprise
architecture is one instrument of IG
governance it's not the whole thing
yeah okay so yeah let's dive deeper into
the topic what is enterprise how do you
do enterprise architecture what does it
consist of what are these single things
to do
whoo yeah good question first of all I
would say you could look what what else
happens in the CIO office kind of like
if you say enterprise architecture has
to deal with governing your application
portfolio or your RT function and you
can see what else happens in the CIO
office the next thing you find there is
IT strategy IT strategy is kind of like
the IT part of a company's energy and
also project portfolio management and
then you find enterprise architecture
sometimes it's the same guy who does all
of this in as the head office yeah or
office or something yeah a post like
that so what does the Enterprise
Architect do first of all you should be
involved in IT strategy yeah
because as an Enterprise Architect you
really have to know your business
because if you do not know what drives
your business what are the value
creation mechanisms and so on you cannot
make really much useful decisions about
how to govern your portfolio or how to
steer its first thing so you need to
understand your business you need to
understand the business strategy and you
need to
come up with ideas how to transform this
into nighty strategy or you can do it
even vice versa in a way that you say
okay here we've got a very smart idea
that could even move or shake our
business strategy because maybe you put
IT in a new product or a new process and
then this could even mean that actually
transforms your business model the next
thing you have to do is application
portfolio management it's kind of like
the next big thing because you were
sitting on 200,000 or 4,000 applications
each each has a few hundred a few
thousand function points which is the
dimension normal project useless and you
need to decide what's what's gonna
happen to these guys yeah are they gonna
be retired will you invest will you keep
some stable everything also kind of like
you have to look at that portfolio and
come up with decisions what to do with
it how to evolve it in the future and
this is a job you're never done with
kind of like it's not like a project you
start at the end that you're you're done
you're ready application portfolio
management this is a permanent process
and if you have done all those strategic
things then you need to get your power
on the road so you need some kind of
transformation mechanism so you have one
for example which is all kinds of models
and and tools and putting all your
strategies and models into some tools
that makes them visually available to
all the achieve stuff that's called
modeling and then you have to formulate
guidelines for your IT department and
then you have to make sure that
guidelines are really transformed into
what happens in the company and this is
what people would call architecture
governance or you can also call it
tracking the project portfolio
and tracking the project so that people
don't turn it back on you and do what
they want to do so the strategy is very
nice but if people do not act on it it's
yeah you can as well have a piece of
paper and okay
it's business process modeling also part
of it I mean as enterprise architecture
purchase between business and IT who's
who's responsible for business process
modeling IT business depends depends
first of all it depends a bit in the
company and history who's doing business
process models the ideal stage would be
that IT and business do it together for
example if they have some very advanced
projects they would sit down and charge
the business processes and then
implement them together it's kind of
like the highest and best form whenever
you have a division of labor here and
whenever the division is too high or too
deep border or something this is not
very good for the effectiveness of the
whole thing yeah so as you kind of said
business processes have to be in sync
with all the other models and with the
application portfolio because you need
two applications that support the
business processes yes it's not always
so that the same people would do it but
they have to collaborate very closely
together okay
as I said the ideal case and ideally at
least in my life means I've never seen
it is the ITA and the business are
closely working together having the same
go sitting in the same board meetings
and try to gain the best out of the
things they have I always seen I team to
quite separate it from business in my
past
unfortunately so what do you do to get
business alignment how do you get
business and into the discussion and
yeah get it working yeah this is indeed
one of the tougher questions yes you
have you see me sinking or university
okay you you have several levels of
alignment here you could first let's say
ask the business what they are after and
what they want and often they will not
being able to answer you this is kind of
like the worst
yeah because means you do not work
together you kind of you wait for them
to tell you what they want and just
never really works but not so so unusual
actually at least in the huge
cooperations I know yeah this is kind of
like the 80% case you know mmm but some
people would say yeah okay why is it a
bad it can work but it's like you have a
company or state or anything we're kind
of like everything works as ordered so
this can work and work and work can be
pretty boring and can be enough but in a
very competitive world this is simply
not what's hot enough or fast enough or
challenging enough so the next step
would be what I told when doing an IT
strategy would be okay you sit together
with the business guys mmm and you think
about how would say or how would you
want to support
Ziya strategy strategy and not their
detailed requirements but what would you
do to support their strategy and their
business strategy in their value
creation model this is this is already
better and not all companies really
execute it yeah so if you're at that
level you're already better I would say
and then
better levels are when as I said before
those business processes when the border
between business and IT disappears and
you have mixed teams who would work on
new value creation models that leverage
IT and new presence ideas and who have
the capabilities to implement this in
very short time so in this case you
would not have alignment or something
you would just work closely together and
you're working on the same thing and you
need not kind of like adjust yourself to
somebody who's running in front of you
but you're running together and Finance
is kind of like the best level you can
achieve you know but I think that's
great advice to get out of the simple
execution mode and show that you can
help implementing the business strategy
I mean after all they they just want to
make a good job so most of the time in
my experience they don't see that IT
really helps them they see it only as a
cost factor and if you're just in
execution mode and to what they want or
order it's understandable that they are
in this mode so yeah it's kind of if you
only do what the customer wants or ask
for then you're in the commodity sector
it's like a discounter and in Germany we
have ID and all those this conscious for
food stuff were very cheap and they have
a cutthroat competition they have
absolute commodities and it's not much
fun working for them and it's also not
much fun delivering and he goes for them
because they are so pressed for prizes
it's it's really awful and then if you
look for example at marketing Siri and
saying how do I get out of this price
trap and even find okay you need to
offer you customer some added value or
some guy some things that he he
cool or any any additional value and
then he will start to talk and sing not
only about the price but he was think
about the value of the goods kind of
like the luxury shops for example yeah
so you need to come into this sector out
of the commodity business yeah so okay
okay there are loads of loads may be
that that's too much but there are some
standard models I know in the in the
area and you also touched a few in
Europe book could you give us some idea
what's going on there what are their
four are they good or whatever okay
meaning you could find models for T
government's and similar things of RIT
operations like let's say ITIL or TOGAF
or all this kind of stuff they are older
than let's say actual enterprise
architecture management and say what and
generally not be sufficient to cover the
whole field what I had it for my book is
I observed what people do and I
basically observed that they do
strategies to do application portfolio
modeling to to do modeling and
blueprints that they do tracking of
project portfolios and projects and
that's about it and if you look at
different industries such as automotive
or banking or insurance or even
transportation you will find that most
of the practitioner Enterprise
architects are doing exactly those
things and it was very yeah kind of like
a bit astonishing a very interesting to
see when we did a course or a lecture
and parts them and we had for practicing
architects over there from those four
different industries but they had all a
very similar set of models and they were
all doing very similar saying
so you can say mmm kind of like the art
is developing into one direction yeah
but actual models like ITIL autograph or
Koba door so do not really cover it yeah
it doesn't matter the practitioners know
what to do yet yes it's same year I
never really used any of the standard
marbles always always
yeah used homegrown stuff if you like it
but a bit different view here at least
from my point of view on the blue blue
print stuff do you think there are any
standards out there that should be
followed or our our already you are
usable yes is the point here is give me
a problem and I can propose a solution
so there's no such thing as a universal
blueprint for the universal IT
application just let's say you have
blueprints for software families such as
tank operations simulators yeah so this
has got nothing to do with let's say a
web 2.0 something application so what
people would often see as the universal
blueprint would be such a blueprint for
a big web application where you have a
portal server and integration capability
and some security appliances and a
database and firewall and and whatever
here so you can find these blueprints
they are one kind of blueprints but
usually for each family of problem
services family or kind of a blueprint
so the best recommendation you could
make is that you should you are kind of
like use Google and steal the most you
can find and then you get your blueprint
and for the very common problems you
always have company
like IBM or Oracle and so on
who would propose something that fits
most companies and you can adopt it and
then you're basically done yeah okay
maybe we can jump a bit back to it to
one of the points you made a few
questions before it's an IT strategy I'm
I mean one of the problems I always had
the most CIOs don't really have IT
strategy to be honest usually the only
factor they have is yeah cost pressures
getting constant in ya down but what
what's an IT charge how do you get an IT
strategy what are the things involved
here because that's the other key
driving what if hey I mean if you don't
have a strategy where do you move to
with your enterprise architecture mm-hm
first of all very good question and
second what you mentioned that most
companies do not have one it's also very
true and very very valid observation you
can go even one step before that you if
you look ahead big even big corporations
you will find many many of them who do
not have a business value creation model
or something they just do their daily
job and they do it and that's about it
and as long as no aggressive competitor
appears and they have a good profit and
they have no reason to invest in
strategy and yeah so if you need
practical help on how to do it you can
look into two kinds of sources mmm one
is by a former gardener vice president
mrs. Marion broadband she's written a
book called in you seer or leader and
this will give you some advice on the
process how to formulate an IT strategy
first from so-called business Maxim's
this kind of lead sentences
for your business and the new derive our
G Maxim's
this is the second best thing you can do
the first best thing is to do a
full-blown strategy workshop with your
senior management and board members to
first define a business strategy and
then go on and boil this down or to
refine this in the direction of an IT
strategy explaining all this it's a bit
too much for this year or for this
interview you have from Gartner alone
you have about thousand to 2,000 pages
of materials on how to do it you can
even refer to classics on strategy from
Clausewitz you can read books by God now
you can read books by Mintzberg and
whoever had there's a whole truckload of
books on strategy you need nos yeah but
you will find a lot of hints maybe one
thing here I just want to get your
opinion on this because you said it it
like at least in my opinion you need a
business strategy to get an IT strategy
but is is it really true can you have an
IT strategy without a business strategy
as well yes no problem
it's indeed a very common situation
let's say you are the poor enterprise
architect and you write and department
head level and the guys sitting on top
of you are the board members and if they
have some conscience for status they
would not talk to you yeah because
you're our only department heads so they
wouldn't talk to you about strategy or
you can even find company whereas a
strategy so secret it's restricted only
to the board
yeah yeah and then you have to come up
with an IT strategy without having a
company strategy but if you look at this
gardner stuff you find arrays and lots
of questions and kind of like a
mattresses where you
are able to re-engineer from what the
company's actually doing an IT strategy
that supports what the company is
actually doing today yeah this is better
than nothing
yeah but it's not really good because
you're doing so energy has something
that is directed to towards the future
yeah and it's very tough if you don't
know what they're gonna come up with in
five years to start building the
applications today that support what
they want to do if you don't know it
yeah if they won't tell you or if out of
hierarchical reasons they will not talk
to you you know which is indeed not so
uncommon at least in Europe don't know
what it's like in the States but in
Europe eeeh we have sometimes mobility
yeah
and no good guys will not talk to the
techies I think it's not so different
all over the world ok ok so we already
mentioned a few of the problems you have
to face as an enterprise architects what
are other typical stuff that gets into
your work risks problems whatever first
of all the one we talked about is if
your senior management doesn't talk to
you about so Jeanne you really have a
pro you really have a problem doing the
right things the next thing is the tears
often a big divide yeah we mentioned
this already between business and IT if
if IT guys are perceived as the stupid
techies and if the IT guys perceives the
business guys as the business guys who
never know what they want in future then
you have a problem in your company yeah
next one we also mentioned if top
management is not interested in surgery
long term planning
and you can also expect to have a very
tough job because you will not be very
effective as I kind of like outlined I
mentioned before also a very common one
is that you're sitting at the wrong
place in the hierarchy
s-see enterprise architecture so if
you're not a direct report to the CIO or
if you're reporting to let's say some
lower department head yeah then you will
not be very effective
right from the start yeah so mmm
I have an array of let's say 9:00 10:00
or so such very common pitfalls make
your life as an enterprise architect
sometimes be difficult or sometimes even
miserable there are indeed some somehow
common but you need to deal with some be
a bit patient and then yeah do the right
thing and keep doing it and wait until
you maybe get out of the manager I've
seen especially how to manage your boss
stuff which is pretty funny ok maybe at
least my last last question maybe
enterprise architecture is a lot of work
how do you do you with the the situation
that you don't slow down everything too
much that it doesn't get too formal I
mean at least in these times everybody
has to be HR and fast and and moving as
fast as you can and if you add too much
of the administration overhead here it's
difficult so what do you do there yes
first of all you shouldn't want to add
too much of administration overhead if
you look at enter products models then
there's a very common pattern which was
mined by a guy called
it's called mile wide inch deep yeah so
the basic mode of operations modeling
you should have if you're doing
enterprise architecture it's not to go
maximum deep and become maximum detail
but to get the overview you need with
the minimum of formalism and modeling
and information that you could imagine
so this is what they call inch deep yeah
if you need to to decide honest
uncertain matters you would be forced to
do a deep draw
yeah but this is kind of like you're
doing a deep drilling project
architecture you're modeling some stuff
you look at more details and then you
would do the detail you need for this
decision and then you let it let it go
and you will not do this on your whole
portfolio if you say that this is too
much bureaucracy at all yeah and if you
say this is not even good to know all
your photos and applications and have an
application handbook that lists them
yeah then I have a nice military analogy
here for all the guys about kind of like
development of safety and security
technologies if you look at cars let's
say 40 years ago yeah then safety belts
and let's say airbags were absolutely
unknown because they were not invented
yeah later on airbags were invented for
Mercedes s-class which is their
top-notch car you know about I don't
know let's say 25 30 years ago or so
today you would have airbags even in a
VW Polo which is one of the smallest
cars from false bang yeah so you will
see that all those security technologies
will get more and more affordable now
because
as the more experienced you getting some
more you produce the cheaper it gets
yeah because it's standard procedures
and it's kind of like dripping down from
the very expensive cars to the small
cars and this is kind of comparable to
like those technologies and techniques
are dripping down from the very large
fortune 100 companies to the smaller
ones you can observe the same with let's
say marketing or controlling and all
these practices that were not in place
50 years ago that were experimented with
50 years ago in very large companies and
today everybody has it young today
everybody even in a 10 people company
knows about marketing it's yeah I asked
somebody 25 years ago and he would say
marketing what do we need it yeah so
enterprise architecture is pretty much
comparable to that it's a management
technique which is currently dripping
down from very large corporations to
smaller ones and which is developing as
an art and as a practice and which is
also some kind of a safety technology
which ensures you against let's say any
bad evolve months in in business and
keep in keep into actually the portfolio
up-to-date and stuff like that I mean
it's cost a lot of your yeah and even
the regulation stuff at least yeah push
you a bit in this direction I would say
yes
if you look at the stuff like let's say
socks yeah which I hope we will not see
in 10 years from now any longer but if
you look at all these measures and for
example if you want to be Sox compliance
which you need to be if you're a
publicly traded company in the US
then you need to be COBIT compliant
because this is what IT auditors mostly
apply if they want to check IT for Sox
compliance and if you want to be COBIT
compliant you will find a lot of control
questions that point directly towards
enterprise architecture and for example
you also have loss in the asset for
certain government agencies and fields
and government
you also need Enterprise Architecture so
it's even illegal to work without one
yeah it's kind of like again the safety
bouncing fifty years ago nobody had such
a thing today it's illegal to ride
without one yeah so again this
comparison was a security or safety
technology people get more and more
risk-averse and invest more and more in
insurance and Enterprise Architecture at
least some aspects is also kind of
insurance yeah against bad developments
in business and the application
portfolio absolutely agreed so that's
where at least my questions do you want
anything else to add here no no thanks
my cold yeah thank you thank you very
much everybody who's interested in topic
and can read chairman books to read both
kinds book it's really good
it's very practical and not their books
out there but most of them are worried
theoretical and not really practice
relevant so get it and thank you working
again and yeah you're next time thank
you Alex bye
[Music]
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio if you want to get
more information about software
engineering radio or if you want to give
us feedback please go to our website at
se - radio dot net you can also contact
the team at team at SAE - radio net
although we prefer entries in our
comment system on the website so other
people can see what you think
software engineering radio wants to
thank Henning poly for the intro and
outro music as well as Lipson for
providing the bandwidth this episode of
se radio as well as all other episodes
is licensed under Creative Commons
license
see the software engineering radio
website for details